Guide to the Lesbian Community Project 1976-2008
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Lesbian Community Project records
1976-2008
1985-2008
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Davies Family Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 2988-12
Lesbian Community Project
13 cubic feet 26 document cases, 1 card file box, 1 oversize folder, 1 tube
Records of lesbian community and political activism group headquartered in Portland, Oregon. Includes correspondence, minutes of meetings, publications, files on organizations and issues, and photographs. Materials date primarily from the late 1980s to the early 2000s.
Historical Note
In 1985, the Lesbian Community Project (LCP) began its mission to promote, as it states in its first mission statement, the “well-being of the lesbian community through a grassroots organization with an evolving multi-issue, multi-cultural perspective.” Over the course of the next 23 years until closing its doors in 2008, LCP became a champion of lesbians in the greater Portland area as well as the stretches of Oregon and nearby Vancouver, WA. In its history, the LCP has expanded the visibility of Pacific Northwest’s lesbian and gay community as can be seen in grants received, the conferences and programs they offered, the political fights lost and won, the individuals LCP stood behind, the directors who led the charge, and the activities of countless members and volunteers; all of which are part of the collection.
As a grassroots nonprofit organization, LCP records show the establishment of an organization from the initial thoughts of its founding members through the passing of its 20th Anniversary; its connecting ties to the Community Education Project; the by-laws and mission statements that developed over the years to best represent the changing lesbian community; the financial struggle of depending on grants and donations to survive while best serving its community; and the shaping of an organization as the issues and images of the lesbian, gay and transgender community shifted over time.
The LCP collection includes records of administrative, financial, legal, personnel, board of director, committee, media, and membership activities within the organization as well as key social and political issues, events, and organizations of interest to LCP during its tenure. The collection also includes the LCP publication On Track. Letters from the lesbians throughout Oregon in thanks of the LCP can also be found in the collection.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: Administrative records
Series B: Political and social issues
Series C: Lesbian Community Project activities
The collection is open to the public.
The collection was originally housed in the organization's offices in Portland's Union Station. The materials were gathered by the Gay and Lesbian Archives of the Pacific Northwest (GLAPN) and donated to the Oregon Historical Society.
Acquired 2003-2010: Library Accessions 24975, 26081, 261123, 26300, and 27027.
The following materials have been transferred to the artifact collection of the Oregon Historical Society:
On Track Award plaque of 1994-1996 winners
Annie Ocean "Placenta - Tree of Life" original framed artwork
Oral histories received with this collection have been transferred to the oral history collections of the Oregon Historical Society and will be cataloged individually.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Lesiban Community Project--Archives.
Portland (Or.)--Social life and customs.; Portland (Or.)--Societies and clubs.; Portland (Or.)--Social life and customs.
Gay liberation movement--Northwest, Pacific.; Gay liberation movement--Oregon.; Lesbians--Northwest, Pacific.; Lesbians--Oregon.; Lesbians--Societies and Clubs--Northwest, Pacific.; Women--Societies and Clubs--Oregon.; Women--Societies and Clubs--Northwest, Pacific
Gays and Lesbians; Oregon; Portland; Women; Vancouver (Wash.)
Letters (correspondence)
On track
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Administrative Records, 1985-2008; Series A
  - Establishment, 1985-2008
    - By Laws 1987-1988, 1987-2003; 1/1: 1987-1988; 1/2: 1992-1996; 1/3: 2000; 1/4: 2003 (Box-folder 1/1-1/4)
    - Community Education Project (CEP), 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Computer diskettes and compact disks, circa 1985-2008 (Box-folder CFB-1)
    - Executive Director Introductory Manual, State of Affairs, and Director's Reports, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Leases, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Letters of Support & Certificates, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Mission Statement, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Policies, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Proposals, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Protocol, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Retrospectives, 1985-2000 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - State Employment Compliance, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Structure, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Legal Matters
    - Estate of Henry Dew, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Inyoswan vs. Hanvey, 2001 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Paul C. deParne (OCA) vs. LCP et. al., 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2/7-8)
    - Robert Vervloet vs. LCP, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Roma Harvey & Judith Applegate vs. LCP/CEP, 2002 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Employee Information & Positions
    - Anti-Violence Project Coordinator Hiring Information, 1995 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Executive Director Hiring Information, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Internships Applications and Evaluations, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Personnel Policies, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Judith Applegate, Executive Director & Board of Directors, 2001 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Kristen Aspen, Executive Director, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Sara Cleveland, Administrative Assistant, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Sally Cohen, Volunteer Coordinator, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Jann Gilbert, Project & Development Assistant, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - LaVerne Lewis, Executive Director, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Donna Redwig, Executive Director, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Hillary Smith, Anti-Violence Porject Director, 1995 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Short Term Employees, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Board of Directors
    - Annual Reports, 1988-2001 (Box-folder 4/1-4/10)
    - Agendas & Reports, 1985-2002 (Box-folder 4/11-4/15, 5/1-5/6)
    - Maintenance
      - Board Applications, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Board Member Lists, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/8)
      - Board Member Retreats, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/9)
      - Elections, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/10)
      - Letters of Resignation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/11)
      - Miscellaneous, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/12)
      - Policy, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/13)
      - Responsibilities & Duties, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 6/1-6/6)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1995-2007 (Box-folder 7/1-7/8)
  - Committees
    - Community Center Committee, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Development Committee, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Diversity Committee, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Election Committee, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - Membership Committee, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - Miscellaneous Committees, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Political Effectiveness Committee, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Speakers Bureau Committee, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Steering Committee Agendas & Reports, 1986-1995; 8/9: 1986; 8/10-8/11: 1987; 8/12: 1988; 8/13: 1989; 8/14: 1995 (Box-folder 8/9-8/14)
    - Steering Committee Meeting Minutes, 1987-1988; 8/15: 1987; 8/16-8/17: 1988 (Box-folder 8/15-8/17)
  - Correspondance
    - Community Mail, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Harrassment Call Log, 1993 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Financial Records
    - Budget, 1986-2006; 9/2-9/7: 1986-1993; 10/1-10/13: 1993-2006; 2004 not available (Box-folder 9-10)
    - CEP (Community Education Project)
      - CEP Budget, 1993-1995; Separate folders for years 1993-1995 (Box-folder 11/1-11/3)
      - CEP IRS Documents & Bylaws, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 11/4)
      - CEP Tax Exemption Applications, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Deposits & Withdrawals
      - Bank Statements, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 11/6)
      - CEP Deposits, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 11/7)
      - LCP Deposits, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 11/8)
    - Income
      - Donations, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 11/9)
      - Fundraising, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 11/10)
    - Grants
      - A Territory Resource, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/1)
      - Astraea, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/2)
      - Ben & Jerry Foundation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/3)
      - Equity Foundation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/4)
      - Pride Foundation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/5)
      - Resist, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/6)
      - Mckenzie River Gathering (MRG) Foundation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/7)
      - VOCA, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 12/9)
    - Financial Reports
      - CEP Reports, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/1)
      - LCP Reports, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/2)
    - Government
      - 501c3 Nonprofit Status, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/3)
      - c3 & c4 Status, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/4)
      - Corporation (LCP & CEP), 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/5)
      - OR State Tax Forms, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/6)
      - Quarterly Tax Reports, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/7)
      - Tax Audit 2002 (Box-folder 13/8)
      - Tax Exemption Forms, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 13/9)
      - Tax Forms & Information, 1986-1999; Folder for 13/10: 1986-1989; 13/11: 1990; 13/12: 1991; 13/13: 1992; 13/14: 1993; 13/15: 1994; 13/16: 1995; 13/17: 1996; 13/18: 1997; 13/19: 1998; 13/20: 1999 (Box-folder 13/10-13/20)
    - Insurance
      - Commercial Property Insurance, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 14/1)
      - Health & Dental Insurance, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 14/2)
      - Liability Insurance, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 14/3)
      - Life Insurance, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 14/4)
      - Workers Compensation Insurance, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 14/5)
      - Workers Compensation Audit 1991 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - Media
    - Advertisements for LCP/On Track, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 14/7)
    - Graphics, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/1)
    - Pamphlets by LCP, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/3)
    - LCP Ads, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/2)
    - Reprint Permissions, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/5)
    - Publicity Strategies, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/4)
    - Posters, undated (Box-folder Oversize folder)
    - Parade banners (2), undated (Box-folder Tube)
  - Membership
    - Annual Member Meetings, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/6)
    - Membership Communications, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/7)
    - Membership Profiles, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/8)
    - Membership Questionnaire Results 1986 (Box-folder 15/9-15/10)
  - Volunteering, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 15/11)
- Political & Social Issues, Series B
  - Baltimore, MD Gay & Lesbian Civil Rights Bill 1988 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Oregon State Legislation
    - Ballot Measure 7 (Equal Protection Amendment – Springfield, OR) 1994 (Box-folder 16/2)
    - Ballot Measure 8 (Anti-Non Discrimination Employment – OCA) 1988 (Box-folder 16/3)
    - Ballot Measure 9 (Sexual Minority Discrimination – OCA) 1991 (Box-folder 16/4)
    - HB 3211 (Foster Parents, 1989), HB 3482 (Surrogacy Agreements, 1991) & Child Emancipation (1984), 1984-1991 (Box-folder 16/5)
    - LC 241 (Campaign Contributions) 1990 (Box-folder 16/6)
    - SB 606 (Bias Crime Reporting & Training) 1990 (Box-folder 16/7)
    - SB 708 & 631 (Tenant Rights) 1989, 1991 (Box-folder 16/8)
  - Non-Oregon Political Activities
    - Hospital Visitation & Guardianship Lawsuit 1986-1988 (Box-folder 16/9)
    - New York State Governor’s Task Force on Gay Issues 1986 (Box-folder 16/10)
  - Oregon Political Activities
    - Hate Crime Legislation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 16/11)
    - Lobbying Resources, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/1)
    - Multnomah County: Metropolitan Human Relations Commission, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 17/2)
    - Oregon Citizens Alliance (OCA), 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/3)
    - Portland City Police & Gay Community, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/4)
    - Portland City Police: Glove Use Controversy 1989-1990 (Box-folder 17/5)
    - Portland Civil Rights Ordinance 1991 (Box-folder 17/6)
  - Social Issues
    - Anti-LGBTQ Violence, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/7)
    - Homophobia & Homophobia Propaganda, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/8)
    - LCP Compilations, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/9)
    - Lesbian Health, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/10)
    - LGBTQ Academic Essays, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 17/11)
  - Ephemera
    - Alix Dobkin's adventures in women's musem (songbook), 1976 (Box-folder 18/1)
    - The gay desk calendar, 1990 (Box-folder 18/2)
    - Stepping out of line: a workbook on lesbianism and feminism by Nym Hughes, Yvonne Johnson, and Yvette Perreault, 1984 (Box-folder 18/3)
      Personal copy of Tamara Janetdatter, with notes and essay
    - You're never too old to love--original drawing by Carolyn Bass, 1985 (Box-folder 18/4)
  - LGBTQ Organizations
    - LCP Compilation, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 18/5)
    - National LGBTQ Organizations, 1985-2008; Fund for Human Dignity; GLSEN (Gay, Lesbian & Straight Education Network); HRC (Human Rights Campaign); Lavender Law; Lesbian Rights Project; March on Washington; National Education Association Gay & Lesbian Caucus; NGLTF (National Gay & Lesbian Task Force); PFLAG (Parents, Families & Friends of Lesbians and Gays) (Box-folder 18/6)
    - National & Regional LGBTQ-Supportive Organizations & Businesses, 1985-2008; Center for Democratic Renewal; Department of Health & Human Services; Ms. Foundation for Women; People for the American Way; Women’s Foundation of Oregon & SW Washington (Box-folder 18/7)
    - Non-Oregon LGBTQ Organizations, 1985-2008; Alternative Connections; ALPS (Assoc. of Lesbian Professions) Seattle; Equity Institute; Lesbian Mothers National Defense Fund; Misc; Partners; Women’s Building (Box-folder 19/1)
    - Oregon LGBTQ Organizations, 1985-2008; Hambletun Project (Portland Lesbian Cancer Network); Our House; PFLAG Northwest; PPOW (Portland Professional Organization of Women); Right to Privacy PAC (Box-folder 19/2)
    - Oregon LGBTQ-Supportive Organizations & Businesses, 1985-2008; ACLU Oregon; Allies People to People; ALLOW (Alliance of Local Organizations for Women); Campaign for Parity; Citizens for 1 Oregon “The Coalition”; Coalition for Human Dignity; Misc; Oregon Women’s Conference; Oregon Women’s Political Caucus (Box-folder 19/3)
- LCP Activities, Series C
  - Events & Conferences
    - A Forest Fantasy Fundraiser, 1990 (Box-folder 20/1)
    - Affirming Our Choice Conference, 1989 (Box-folder 20/2)
    - Lesbian Families Conference, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 20/3-20/5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 20/6)
    - New Year’s Eve Parties, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 21/1)
    - Party with Pride, 1988 (Box-folder 21/2)
    - Performers Contracted by LCP, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 21/3)
    - Pride at the Pittock, 1987 (Box-folder 21/4)
    - Portland’s First Lesbian Conference 1986 (Box-folder 21/5-21/6)
    - Walk Against Hate, 1992 (Box-folder 21/7)
  - LCP Affiliated/Partnered Events & Programs
    - Chase the Blues Dance (with National Organization of Women – NOW), 1988 (Box-folder 22/1)
    - Coke Boycott Project, 1989 (Box-folder 22/2)
    - Gay Pride Events 1982 (Box-folder 22/3-22/4)
    - Gay Pride Events 1991 & 1996 (Box-folder 22/5)
    - International Women’s Day, 1995 (Box-folder 22/6)
    - LCP & Cascade AIDS Project (CAP), 1985-2008 (Box-folder 22/7)
    - National Lesbian Conference 1988-1989 (Box-folder 22/8)
    - National Lesbian Conference Portland Meeting 1989 (Box-folder 22/9)
    - Public Conversation Project, 2001 (Box-folder 22/10)
    - Starlight Parade Gay & Lesbian Float 1989 & 1990 (Box-folder 22/11)
  - Programs & Projects
    - Anti-Violence Hotline, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/1)
    - Bingo, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/2)
    - Film Festivals & Film Nights, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/4)
    - LCP Community Packet, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/5)
    - LCP Community Questionnaire, undated (Box-folder 23/6)
    - LCP Resource Guides, 1986, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994 (Box-folder 23/7-23/9)
    - Lesbian Healthcare Directory, 2002 (Box-folder 23/10)
    - Lesbian Health Project & Safe Sex Kits, 1995 (Box-folder 23/11)
    - Seniors Programs, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/12)
    - Softball Tournament, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23/13)
    - Yappy Dog No on 9 Donations Campaign, 1991 (Box-folder 23/14)
    - Youth Leadership Camps, 2000 (Box-folder 23/15)
  - On Track Journal
    - Content, 1987-2008 (Box-folder 24/1)
    - Graphics, 1987-2008 (Box-folder 24/2)
    - Log & Tasks, 1987-2008 (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Procedures, 1987-2008 (Box-folder 24/4)
    - Production, 1987-2008 (Box-folder 24/5)
    - Publication Issues 1987-1990 (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Publication Issues 1991-1994 (Box-folder 24/7)
    - Publication Issues 1995-1999 (Box-folder 25/1)
    - Publication Issues 2000-2004 (Box-folder 25/2)
    - Publication Issues 2005-2008 (Box-folder 25/3)
    - Supplimental Newsletters, 1987-2008 (Box-folder 25/4)
  - Photos, 1985-2008 (Box-folder 26/1-26/8)
    Candids and professional photos, mostly from LCP events.